Finding Aid for the Elaine Barkin Musical Compositions and Papers PASC-M.0059
UCLA Library Special Collections
Elaine Barkin musical compositions and papers
1955-2010
UCLA Library Special Collections
Barkin, Elaine
PASC-M.0059
15.2 Linear Feet (31 boxes)
9 Audiovisual Carriers (4 records, 5 open reel audiotapes)
12 Born-digital Carriers (12 optical discs)
This collection primarily contains musical compositions and professional writings by composer Elaine Barkin.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elaine Barkin, 1987-2010.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303553606533
Biography
Composer, writer, and performer Elaine Barkin was born December 15, 1932 in New York City. She graduated from Queens College, CUNY and Brandeis University (MFA, 1954 and Ph.D, 1971) and studied composition at the Berlin Hochschule für Musik in the 1950s. Barkin taught at Queens College (1964-1970), the University of Michigan (1970-1974), and Princeton (1974), before joining the faculty at UCLA in 1974, teaching music composition and theory; she retired from UCLA in 1997. Barkin also served as an editor for the journal Perspectives of New Music from the mid-1960s to 1980s, and wrote numerous essays for the publication and other music journals, including Open Space Magazine, which she co-founded. In the 1980s, Barkin undertook several excursions to Bali to study gamelan music and interview Indonesian musicians.
Elaine Barkin has composed numerous musical works, including those for strings, piano, percussion, harp, woodwind, horns, gamelan, and voice.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of draft and reproduction scores, sketches, and some completed versions of Elaine Barkin's musical compositions; writings and material relating to editorial work for the journal Perspectives of New Music; and writings for other publications. Also present is a small amount of material concerning Barkin's other professional endeavors, including her involvement with the Society for Music Theory and her interest in Balinese music; personal correspondence; ephemera; and audio recordings of some of her works.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1. Musical compositions
Series 2. Perspectives of New Music
Series 3. Other writings and professional endeavors
Series 4. Personal correspondence and files
Series 5. Audio recordings
Series 6. Film: Lapis
Related Material
UCLA Music Library has individual scores and recordings of Barkin's work. Please search the UCLA Library Catalog.
Universities and colleges -- California -- Los Angeles -- Faculty -- Archives.; Women composers -- United States -- Archives.; Barkin, Elaine, 1932- --Archives.
- Series 1. Musical compositions, 1955-2007
  Scope and Content
  This series consists of draft and reproduction scores, sketches, and some completed versions of Barkin's compositions, arranged alphabetically by title. Material for a few titles includes related correspondence, notes, performance graphics and photographs.
  - 4 Little Machine Pieces, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 18 Easy and Moderately Difficult Pieces for Pedal and/or Lever Harp, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - At the Piano, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ballade, [2003] (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Barely There, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - [Be]coming Together Apart, [1987] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chaconne Variations, [1956] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CODA: leave-taking, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - De Amore, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 11, Folder 7-10)
    Material includes performance photographs and props (Box 11).
  - Demeter and Persephone, [1986] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Duo for Two Violins and Three Little Duos, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Ebb Tide, [1977] (Box 3, Folder 3, Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Essay for Orchestra, [1957] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ... For My Friends' Pleasure..., [1995] (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - For Suite's Sake, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Four Short Pieces for Piano, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gamélange, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
  - Harp Pieces, 2002-2003 (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - Impromptu, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - ...In Its Surrendering..., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Inward and Outward Bound, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
  - Legong Dreams, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Libretto, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Media Speak, 1981, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    Material includes clippings and notes (Box 12).
  - Mixed Modes, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Movement for String Quartet, [1955] (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Music for Piano 4-Hands, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - NB Suite, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ode, 2002-2003 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
  - ...Out of the Air..., 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Parlor Music, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Past Is Part Of (Graphics), [1984] (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Piano Suite, [2007] (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Play and Ghost Sarabande for violoncello, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - play it AS it lays (Graphics), [1979] (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Plein Chant, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Plus Ça Change [La Même Plus Changé], 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - ...Poem..., [1999] (Box 1, Folder 7, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Prelude & Suonata, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Prim Cycles, [1972] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Refrains, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Quilt Piece, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Rhapsodies, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Six Compositions for Piano, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sketch, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - ...The Sky..., [1978] (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Song for Sarah, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 12, Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sound Play, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Still Life, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - String Quartet, [1969] (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - String Trio, 1976, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3-4, Box 8)
  - Suite for Piano, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - ...The Supple Suitor..., [1978] (Box 7, Folder 5-9)
  - Tambellan Suite, [2003], 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 14, Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Three Cummings Sky Choruses, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Time Out, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Touching All Bases, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Two as One, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Two Emily Dickinson Choruses, [1976-1977] (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Warna/Colors, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Sketches and unfinished works, 1974-2002 (Box 9, Folder 4, Box 13, Folder 4-5)
    Includes [Interlude] (1974) and [Strings?] (2001-2002) [Box 13], and a sketch for a piece on solitude never composed (1983) [Box 9].
  - Unidentified drafts and sketches, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-3, Box 9, Folder 5-7)
  - Works by others, 1992-1995 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    Includes Anne LeBaron's Solar Music, and Renee T. Coulombe's Four (and...) for Solo Piano, Triage I for Seven Performers, and Triage II: A Map of the Known Universe for Seven Performers. Also present are additional scores submitted by various composers to Perspectives of New Music for their tribute issue to Aaron Copland (see Box 17, folders 7-8 for related material).
- Series 2. Perspectives of New Music, 1972-2004
  Barkin wrote numerous essays for Perspectives of New Music and also served as an editor for the journal from the mid-1960s to the 1980s. This series consists of her PNM writings and of correspondence related to her editorial work, in addition to production material for a few individual issues. Writings for other journals and publications are located in Series 3.
  - Subseries 1. Writings, [1975]-2004
    Contains drafts, corrected proofs and notes for Barkin's essays and other works for PNM. Titles are arranged chronologically.
    - Review of Charles Rosen's Arnold Schoenberg, [1975] (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Conversation Piece (for Milton Babbitt), 1976 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Post Impressions: Arthur Berger's Trio, and a Postlude, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
    - A Dedication, Five ADmusements, & A Digression, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Earl Kim's Earthlight, [1981] (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Conversations with Rachel Rosenthal, [1981-1983] (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Responses from Women Composers in the US, 1982, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - On Being a Composer, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - either/other (concerning the work of Susan McClary), 1989-1992 (Box 15, Folder 1-5)
    - ... typescript, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - reexperiencing Language, as a Music revisited, 1999-2001 (Box 15, Folder 7-9)
    - 9 Ben-Collages & VI Fragments from a Never-Ending Work in Progress for the Ben Boretz Festschrift, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2. Correspondence, 1972-1993
    Correspondence received also contain some copies of outgoing letters by Barkin.
    - Letters received A-R, 1972-1984 (Box 16, Folder 1-11)
    - Letters received S-Z, 1976-1984 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
    - Letters sent, 1977-1982 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1993 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Bulk is letters received by PNM; also includes letters sent to Barkin by PNM, mostly about her writings for the journal.
  - Subseries 3. Individual issues
    - Material related to Vol. 17 No. 1 (Fall/Winter 1978), 1978, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Notes, correspondence, and other material.
    - Material related to Vol. 19 No. 1/2 (Fall 1980/Summer 1981), 1980-1982 (Box 17, Folder 7-8, Box 10, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and scores from composers for a tribute issue to Aaron Copland.
    - Vol. 17 No. 2 (Spring/Summer 1979) (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Annotated published edition; contains Barkin's piece Play it AS it lays.
- Series 3. Other writings and professional endeavors, 1968-[2010]
  Series consists of Barkin's writings for other journals and publications, biographical entries for the Grove Dictionary of Music, and her dissertation. Also present is material related to Barkin's editorial work for the anthology Audible Traces: Gender, Identity, & Music; newsletters and other items for several music organizations including the Society for Music Theory; material concerning Barkin's interest in Balinese music; items related to her recordings and music publication; images of an art project; and several folders of ephemera that document Barkin's performances and professional activities.
  - Subseries 1. Writings, 1975-[2010]
    Contains drafts, corrected proofs, notes, and scores for writings, some with related correspondence. Also included are biographical entries written for various editions of the Grove Dictionary of Music, and Barkin's dissertation Pitch-time Structure in Arnold Schoenberg's Opus 23, No. 1: A Contribution Toward A Theory of Nontonal Music.
    - Analysis Symposium: Webern's Orchestra Piece Bewegt, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Gesualdo's Moro Lasso, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Analysis Symposium: Debussy's Pour Les Sixtes: Notes in Progress (3 fols), 1978 (Box 18, Folder 3-5)
    - Arnold Schoenberg's Opus 19/6, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Rhetorical Variations: The Composer in Society, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - A Text on the Music of Harry Partch, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Colloquy and Review, 2000 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Conjunctions, Affinities, and Loose Ends: A Text in Five Parts for G.E.M.S., 2002, 2003 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - e: an anthology (volume 2), music texts & graphics (1967-2003), [2004] (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - Conversations (about Bob Paredes), 2005 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - The Open Space Magazine issue 7 (fall 2005) (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Includes Barkin's BAB's O, Milton Babbitt's Groupwise, and Conversations.
    - Review of Phillip Ramey's Irving Fine, 2006 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Review of Hollis Taylor's Post Impressions, [2009] (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Grove Dictionary of Music entries, 1971-[2010] (Box 19, Folder 7-12)
      Consists of drafts, notes, biographical information, and correspondence from composers relating to entries written by Barkin for various editions of the Grove Dictionary of Music. Some copies of Barkin's published entries, correspondence from Grove, and a contract are also present. Entries include Milton Babbitt, Allan Blank, David Burge, Roger Goeb, Donald Martino, James K. Randall, Henry Weinberg, Peter Westergaard, and Charles Whittenberg.
    - Pitch-time Structure in Arnold Schoenberg's Opus 23, No. 1: A Contribution Toward A Theory of Nontonal Music (dissertation), 1971 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Includes dissertation copy, scores, and critique.
  - Subseries 2. Audible Traces: Gender, Identity, & Music, 1993-1999 (Box 20, Folder 2-6)
    Consists of material relating to publication of Audible Traces, co-edited by Barkin and Lydia Hamessley, published by Carciofoli Verlagshaus, 1999. Material includes drafts of Barkin's preface and Hamessley's introduction, contracts, and correspondence with authors and the publisher. Also included is a zip disk of material for the project (box 31).
  - Subseries 3. Society for Music Theory, 1977-1993 (Box 21, Folder 1, Box 20, Folder 7-11)
    Barkin served on the Executive Board and the Program Committee for the Society for Music Theory. Material includes correspondence, minutes, membership and program material, and a newsletter. Also present is Barkin's 1993 presentation Rules of One's Own, given to the SMT's Committee on the Status of Women, which also appeared in Audible Traces and e: an anthology.
  - Subseries 4. Balinese music, [1990]-1998 (Box 21, Folder 2-4)
    While at UCLA, Barkin was involved in the UC-wide New Music in Bali project, which promoted the creation of new works for gamelan and sponsored visiting composers from Bali. Barkin also received funding to travel to Bali, and conducted interviews with composers and musicians from 1988 to 1990. Material includes interview transcripts, items regarding the UC Pacific Rim Research Program, and correspondence.
  - Subseries 5. Recordings and score publication, 1974-1984 (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
    Includes correspondence and contracts from the Association for the Promotion of New Music; Boelke-Bomart, Inc. & Mobart Music Publications, Inc.; and Composers Recordings, Inc.
  - Subseries 6. American Society of University Composers Newsletter, 1968-1986 (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
  - Subseries 7. Contemporary Music Newsletter, 1968-1977 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 8. Ephemera, 1969-2009
    Primarily contains programs, flyers, and other ephemera concerning performances of Barkin's music and professional activities. Some related correspondence and clippings are also included. Items are filed in rough chronological order (reverse order within some folders).
    - 1969-1989 (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
    - 1990-1999 (fol 1) (Box 23, Folder 1-7)
    - 1999 (fol 2)-2009 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries 9. Hub cap masks (art project), 2006 (Box 31)
    Two CDs of jpg images of Barkin's hub cap masks, created 2002-2005.
- Series 4. Personal correspondence and files, 1972-2004
  Consists of letters received from colleagues and friends, primarily fellow composers. Barkin arranged her correspondence in rough chronological order (some folders are in reverse order).
  - Correspondence, 1972-1980 (Box 24, Folder 5-7)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1988 (Box 25, Folder 1-8)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1999 (Box 26, Folder 1-8)
  - Correspondence, 1988-2005 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Jack Body, 1989-1994 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and subject file: Diamanda Galás, 1984-1995 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    Includes Barkin's lecture "Notes for Diamanda Galás and her Plague Mass" given at UCLA October 1993.
  - Subject file: John Whitney, 1984, 2004 (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Series 5. Audio recordings, 1969-2008
  Contains recordings of Barkin's works in various formats, including reels (5 inch and 7 inch), CDs, and audio cassettes. Dates are those of recording.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Use of audio material requires production of listening copies.
  - Subseries 1. Reels
    - 5 Inch (Box 28)
      - Ebb Tide, 1980
      - Ebb Tide, Sound Play, 1977, 1978
      - Plein Chant, [1981]
      - String Trio, undated
      - ... the Supple Suitor..., undated
      - Three Poems by e.e. cummings, 1980
    - 7 Inch (Box 29, Box 30)
      - Barkin - Sollberger (2 reels), undated
      - De Amore, 1982
      - Ebb Tide, undated
      - Ebb Tide, 1982
      - Five Compositions for Piano, 1969
      - Media Speak, 1982
      - Media Speak, 1982
      - Plein Chant, 1979
      - Prim Cycles, 1981
      - Refrains, 1969
      - Six Pieces for Piano, 1969
      - Six Pieces for Piano, 1977
      - String Quartet, 1973
      - To Piety More Prone, 1983
      - Two Dickinson Choruses, 1978
  - Subseries 2. CDs
    - Ballade, Praeambulum for AB, Sara's Dance, Umbrella Steps, When the Wind Blows, Violin Duo, End Piece, 2007 (Box 28)
    - Chaconne Variations, undated (Box 28)
    - Coda- Leavetaking, Barely There, 2006 (Box 28)
    - Easy Harp Pieces and Tambellan Suite, undated (Box 28)
    - Four MIDI Pieces and Gamelan, undated (Box 28)
    - For My Friends' Pleasure, undated (Box 28)
    - Legong Dreams, Ebb Tide, undated (Box 28)
    - Midi and Ars Nova, 2008 (Box 28)
    - Midi Pieces, 2006 (Box 28)
    - Mixed Modes, String Trio, Song for Sarah, undated (Box 28)
    - Piano Music, [2007] (Box 28)
    - Piano Music: One on One, Umbrella Steps, Postlude [for AB], Sara's Dance, When the Wind Blows, 2007 (Box 28)
    - Piano Music: Step by Step, Whorl, From the Abbeys, Faygele's Footsteps, 2007 (Box 28)
    - Six Pieces for Piano, undated (Box 31)
    - Three Rhapsodies, Poem, Ode, Song for Sarah, undated (Box 31)
    - Three Short Pieces, undated (Box 31)
    - Three Violin Duets and Essay for Orchestra, undated (Box 31)
    - Violin Duo: Two as One, 2007 (Box 31)
    - Violin Duo: Two as One, MIDI, 2007 (Box 31)
  - Subseries 3. Cassette tapes (Box 31)
    - Bass/ gamelan sketches
    - Touching all Bases, Sketch - Ode [or Wind Sketch]
    - Letter from Peri [?], 1982
  - Notes for unidentified recording, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Series 6. Film: Lapis, undated (Box 31)
  Most likely a 16 mm copy of James Whitney's 1966 experimental film Lapis. UCLA Film and Television Archives holds another copy.
  Use of moving image material requires production of viewing copies.